<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An extracte of the determination, and censure of the doctours of the vniversities of Salamanca and Valledolid touching the vvarres of Ireland, and declaration of the Poape his breve concerning the same vvarres</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11335</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21595</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102978</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838737</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838737</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3125</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11335)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3125)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1153:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An extracte of the determination, and censure of the doctours of the vniversities of Salamanca and Valledolid touching the vvarres of Ireland, and declaration of the Poape his breve concerning the same vvarres</title>
                  <author>Zumel, Francisco, 1540-1607. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>A. Tavernier,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Salamanca :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed by Fr. Franciscus Zumel, Dean of the faculty of Divinity at the University of Salamanca, and 17 others.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>War --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1558-1603 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:3125:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An extracte of the determinacion, and cenſure of the Doctours of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities
of Salamanca and Valledolid touching the vvarres of Ireland, and declaracion of
the Poape his Breve concerning the ſame vvarres.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE moſte noble Prince Hugh O Neill beareth armes againſt the Queene of England, and Englishmen
in defence of the Catholique Religion, to vvit, that he, and all Irishme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvith him may freelie, and vvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout
diſturbance confeſſe, and profeſſe the Catholique faith: vvhich libertie the Queene of England
endeuoreth to debarre them of by foarce of armes. About vvhich vvarre ther are tvvo doubtes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.
The one is, vvhether it belavvfull for Irish Catholiques to fauour by armes, or anny other
vvay the forſaid Prince in this vvarre? The other is, vvhether it be lavvfull for the forſaid Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques,
vvithout incurring mortall ſinne, to feight againſt the ſaid Prince, and helpe the Englishmen, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
in armes, or in anny other vvay, eſpeciallie ſeing by vvithdravving, or denying the ſaid helpe they
expoſe them ſelues to the danger of death, and leeſing all their goodes? And againe, ſeing the Irish
Catholiques are permitted by the Poape to obey the Queene of England, and pay hir tribute, as to
their lavvfull Prince, and therfore it ſeemeth that they may doe all that belongeth to ſubiectes, that is,
to feight againſt hir rebelles, and ſuch as ſeeme to invade, and vſurpe the Country ſubiect to hir obeyſance.</p>
            <p>¶To the good aſſoiling of both vvhich queſtions vve muſt preſuppoſe as certeine, that the Poape may compell by force of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes
(vvhen there are no other meanes to remedy ſo greate a miſchief) ſuch as forſake the Catholique faith, and oppoſe themſelues as
enemies to Catholique Religion. It is likevviſe to be ſet dovvne as certeyn, that the Queene of England doth oppugne Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que
Religion, and ſuffreth not Irishmen to maKe publique profeſsion of Catholique Religion, and that for that cauſe the foreſaid
Prince, and before him others, vvhom the Apoſtolicall letters of the Poape Clement the VIII. mencion, haue vndertaKen vvarre
againſt hir.</p>
            <p>VVhich groundes admitted, the firſt queſtion is eaſilie anſvveared, for ther is no doubte, but that all Catholiques may fauour
the ſaid Prince in his foreſaid vvarre, and that vvith greate merite, and hoape of eternall revvarde. The reaſon is, becauſe the ſaid
Prince ſuſtayneth the ſaid vvarre by authoritie of the Poape to defend the Catholique Religion, for that his Holines doth exhorte
him, and all Chriſtian people thervnto, as may be ſeene by his Holines his letters ſent foorth to this purpoſe, vvherin he graunteth as
greate fauours, and Indulgences to ſuch as fauour this Prince in the ſaid vvarre, as if they ſhould feight againſt the Turques. VVho
therfore can doubte, that the vvarre is iuſt, and of greate merite before Almightie God, vvhich is vndertaKen by ſuch authoritie,
and for ſuch a cauſe?</p>
            <p>As co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the ſecond queſtion it is alſo certeine, that all Catholiques ſinne mortally vvhich follovve the English ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe againſt
the ſaid Prince, nor can not ſaue their ſoules, nor obtaine abſolucion of anny Prieſt, vnleſſe they repent, and forſaKe the english par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te,
and the liKe is alſo to be ſaid of them vvhich fauour the english in that vvarre vvith municion, or victuails, or contribute anny
other vvay, excepte it be by paiyng the ordinarie taxes, vvhich his Holines hath giuen them leaue to pay to the Queene and her
officers. And this aſſertion is prooued by this manifeſt reaſon enſuing, for it is euident by the Poape his letters, that the Queene of
england, and her adherents doe maKe vniuſt vvarre vppon the Prince, and his fauourers: for ſeing his Holines declareth that the
english oppugne the Catholique faith, and that they ought to be fought againſt vvith no leſſe zeale then Turques, and graunteth
the liKe Indulgences to thoſe that feight againſt them as thoſe gaine vvhich feight againſt Turques, vvho can doub<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, but that the
vvarre on the enlish parte is altogether vniuſt? But no man ought to fauour, or be preſent at vniuſt vvarre, vnder paine of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion.
And therfore, thoſe Catholiques ſinne moſte greeuouſlie that follovve the heretiques parte againſt the ſaid Prince, and
all that fauour the vvarre vvith victuails, municions, or anny other meanes that anny vvay paſſe the limites of indifferent allegiance.</p>
            <p>Neither may it auayle anny man to note the Poape his Breue or letters of ſurrepcion, for ſurrepcion can haue no place vvner
ther is no me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of anny peticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at vvhoſe inſtance it vvas granted, but the Poape doth oppenlie ſhevve in thoſe his letters that he and
his Predeceſſours haue of their avvne acorde exhorted the Princes of Ireland, and all faithfull people vnto that vvarre, and to anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the more theru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to he hath granted greate Indulgences to this purpoſe. Hovv therfore can the Poape his letters be noted of ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repcion,
or called conterfeyte vvhich conteyne nothing but an exhortacion vvith greate fauours to ſuch as ſhall aſſent to them?
Neither can the Catholiques fauouring the English parte defend them ſelues by the reaſons brought in the ſecond queſtion, for
a mortall ſinne muſt not be committed, though our life, and <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>l our goods lay on it: but it is plaine, that to further or healpe an
vniuſt vvarre is a mortall ſinne, &amp;c. And it is onely grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to Catholiques to giue to the hereticall Queene ſuch allegea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as oppug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
not oppenlie Catholique Religion. Neither vvas it nor could it be his Holines his intent to permitte them to doe the
Queene ſuch ſeruices as are quite contrarie to his purpoſe of furthering the Catholique faith in Ireland: vvhich to be his purpoſe his
letters doe euidentlie declare.</p>
            <p>By all vvhich it is moſte euidentlie prooued, that the Prince Oneill, and all the Catholiques of Ireland, that beare armes againſt
the hereticall Queene, that oppugneth the Catholique faith, are not rebels, nor vvithdravve not their trve and deve obedience,
neither doe vniuſtlie vſurpe the Queenes countries, or dominion, but doe rather by iuſt vvarre defend them ſelues, and their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie
from vvicKed Tirannie, and defend vvith all their might the Catholique faith, as it becometh good Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Catholiques to doe.
All vvhich aſſercions iointlie, and in particular as they be heere ſett dovvne, all vve vvhoſe names are ſubſcribed doe iudge, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue
as certaine, and moſte trve. Gyuen at Salamanca the ſecond of February. 1603.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>Fr. Franciſcus Zumel, Deane of the facultie of diuinitie.</item>
                     <item>Mag. Ioannes Alphonſus de Curiel, profeſſor of Diuinitie.</item>
                     <item>Fr. Petrus de Herrera, profeſſor of diuinitie.</item>
                     <item>Doct. Franciſ. Sancius.</item>
                     <item>Fr. Dioniſ. Iuberus.</item>
                     <item>Mag. Andreas de Leon.</item>
                     <item>Fr. Petrus de Ledeſma.</item>
                     <item>Fr. Martinus Peraça.</item>
                     <item>All vvhich are Doctours and Maiſters of Diuinitie in the vniuerſitie of Salamanca.</item>
                     <item>D. Franciſcus Sobrino, Deane of the facultie of diuinitie in the uniuerſitie of Valledolid.</item>
                     <item>D. Alphonſus Vaca de Sanctiago.</item>
                     <item>D. Ioannes Garçia Coronel.</item>
                     <item>Magiſ. Fr. Ioannes Negron.</item>
                     <item>D. Torre.</item>
                     <item>Fr. Ioſephus de Luxan.</item>
                     <item>All vvhich be Doctours
and Maisters of Diuinitie in the vniuerſitie of Valledolid.</item>
                     <item>Father Ioannes de Ziguença.</item>
                     <item>Fath. Emanuel de Rojas.</item>
                     <item>Fath. Gaſpar de Menae, profeſſours of Diuinitie in the Colledge of the ſocietie of IESVS
in the forſaid vniuerſitie of Salamanca.</item>
                     <item>Father Petrus Oſorius, ordinarie preacher for the tyme of the ſaid Colledge.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
